Crown Prince of the White House today.
Your Majesty, over to you.
Mr. President, thank you for your gracious hospitality
according to me and my delegation today.
My visit today carries an added meaning
as our country's this year mark 75 years
of exemplary strategic partnership.
However, we had hoped we would be marking
this major milestone during better circumstances
in my region and the world.
Unfortunately, one of the most devastating wars
in recent history continues to unfold in Gaza as we speak.
Nearly 100,000 people have been killed,
injured, or are missing.
The majority are women and children.
We cannot afford an Israeli attack on Rafah.
It is certain to produce another humanitarian catastrophe.
The situation is already unbearable
for over a million people
who have been pushed into Rafah since the war started.
We cannot stand by and let this continue.
We need a lasting ceasefire now.
This war must end.
We must urgently and immediately work
to ensure the sustainable delivery
of sufficient aid to Gaza
through all possible entry points and mechanisms.
And I thank you, Mr. President,
for your support on this.
Restrictions of vital relief aid and medical items
are leading to inhumane conditions.
No other UN agency can do what ANRWA is doing
in helping the people of Gaza
through this humanitarian catastrophe.
Its work in other areas of operation,
especially in Jordan,
where 2.3 million are registered,
is also vital.
It is imperative that ANRWA continues
to receive the support it needs
to carry out its mandate.
The potential threat of Palestinian displacement
beyond the borders of Gaza and the West Bank
is something we view with extreme concern
and cannot be allowed.
At the same time, we must ignore,
we must not ignore,
the situation in the West Bank
and in the holy sites in Jerusalem.
Nearly 400 Palestinians have been killed
in the West Bank since October 7,
including almost 100 children
and over 4,000 injured.
Continued escalations by extremist settlers
in the West Bank and Jerusalem's holy sites
and the expansion of illegal settlements
will unleash chaos on the entire region.
The vast majority of Muslim worshippers
are not being allowed to enter Al-Aqsa Mosque.
Christian churches have also voiced concerns
about increasing and unprecedented restrictions
and threats.
It is also important to stress
that the separation of the West Bank and Gaza
cannot be accepted.
Seven decades of occupation, death and destruction
have proven beyond any doubt
that there can be no peace
without a political horizon.
Military and security solutions
are not the answer.
They can never bring peace.
Civilians on both sides continue to pay
for this protracted conflict with their lives.
All attacks against innocent civilians,
women and children,
including those of October 7,
cannot be accepted by any Muslim,
as I had previously stressed.
We must make sure the horrors
of the past few months since October 7
are never repeated nor accepted
by any human being.
We must, together,
along with Arab partners
and the international community,
step up efforts
to reach a ceasefire in Gaza
and immediately start working
to create a political horizon
that leads to a just and comprehensive peace
on the basis of the two-state solution.
An independent, sovereign,
and viable Palestinian state
with East Jerusalem as its capital.
But living side by side
with Israel
in peace and security,
this is the only solution
that will guarantee peace and security
for the Palestinians
and the Israelis
as well as the entire region.
Your leadership,
my dear friend, Mr. President,
is key to addressing this conflict,
and Jordan is ready to work,
as always,
with you towards peace.
Thank you.